Guide to the Sim A. DeLapp Papers, 1862-1976
Sim A. DeLapp papers 1862-1976
DeLapp, Simeon Alexander
10 Linear Feet circa 13,100 Items
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Durham, North Carolina 27708-0185
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library acquired the Sim A. DeLapp Papers (1862-1976) in three installments 1978, 1980, and 1983 by purchase and gift. The donation was made by Mrs. DeLapp in 1983.
Biographical Note
1897, Dec. 21 Born Davidson County, N.C.
1918 A.B. Trinity College (now Duke University)
1921 LL.B. Trinity College
1921-1926 Practiced law in Lexington, N.C.
1922-1934 Member, Lexington Board of School Commissioners
1926-1946 Member, McCrary and DeLapp law firm
1927, July Married Rose Sexton of Denton, N.C.
1928-1930 Davidson County attorney
1942-1950 Chair, North Carolina State Republican Party
1946-1950 Davison County attorney
1946-1952 Practiced law independently in Lexington, N.C.
1950-1964 Legal counsel for the North Carolina Republican Party
1951-1952 North Carolina State Chairman of Dwight D. Eisenhower's campaign for the presidency
1952-1976 Partner, Lexington law firm that maintained a general and trial practice under various names: DeLapp and Ward, 1952-1966; DeLapp, Ward, and Hedrick, 1966-1972; DeLapp and Hedrick, 1972-1974; DeLapp, Hedrick and Harp, 1974-1975; DeLapp, Hedrick, Harp, and Smith, 1975-1976.
1965-1970 Trustee, Davidson County Community College
1967-1974 Davidson County attorney
1976, Aug. 9 Died, Winston-Salem, N.C.
1983 Named posthumously to the North Carolina GOP Hall of fame
Member of the American, North Carolina, and Davidson County Bar Associations and the Lexington Rotary Club. Member and Elder in the First Evangelical and Reformed Church (later United Church of Christ) in Lexington. Member of the Kiwanis Club.
Collection Overview
The collection chiefly documents DeLapp's long-term involvement with the North Carolina Republican Party at the state and local level. While correspondence comprises the bulk of the collection, there are also some legal and financial papers, writings and speeches, printed material, and clippings. Being Chair of the North Carolina Republican Party (1942-1950) and legal counsel to the party (1950-1964), provided DeLapp access to state party leaders, which is reflected by the correspondents that include J. E. Broyhill, Wilmer D. Mizell, William E. Cobb, and Jesse Helms.
Included is information concerning political appointments, canvassing and registering voters, political campaigns, and political speeches (some made by DeLapp). DeLapp's efforts to promote Republican presidential candidates is highlighted in 1952 when he served as North Carolina State Chairman of Dwight D. Eisenhower's campaign. The earliest corespondence primarily relates to Delapp's father, Alexander T. Lapp, who was sheriff of Davidson County, N.C., from 1906-1912 and 1916-1918. Also represented are DeLapp's responsibilities with the Evangelical and Reformed Church (later the United Church of Christ); information about the DeLapp family and DeLapp's published work, People, Politics, Religion; and concern about the Duke University administration during the 1960s and early 1970s.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Republican Party -- North Carolina
Electioneering -- North Carolina
North Carolina -- Politics and government
Patronage, Political -- North Carolina
Politicians -- North Carolina
Voter registration -- North Carolina
Presidents -- United States -- Election 1952
DeLapp family
Evangelical and Reformed Church
Duke University
DeLapp, Alexander T.
Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969
Broyhill, J. E.
Jonas, Charles Raper
Broyhill, James Thomas, 1927-
Mizell, Wilmer D.
Cobb, William E.
Helms, Jesse
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series
  - 1862-1948, (6 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1949-1951, Aug., (6 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1951, Sept.-1952, June, (7 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1952, July-1953, (7 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1954, Jan.-1957, June, (7 folders) (Box 5)
  - 1957, July-1959, (6 folders) (Box 6)
  - 1960-1964, Apr., (6 folders) (Box 7)
  - 1964, May-1965, June, (7 folders) (Box 8)
  - 1965, July-1966, Sept., (7 folders) (Box 9)
  - 1966, Oct.-1968, May, (6 folders) (Box 10)
  - 1968, June-1970, May, (6 folders) (Box 11)
  - 1970, June-1972, Mar., (6 folders) (Box 12)
  - 1972, Apr.-1973, Oct., (6 folders) (Box 13)
  - 1973, Nov.-1975, Aug., (7 folders) (Box 14)
  - 1975, Sept.-1976, Aug., undated, (4 folders) (Box 15)
- Legal Papers Series
  - 1945-1976 (Box 15)
- Financial Papers Series
  - 1948-1976 (Box 15)
- Addresses and Writings Series
  - 1920-1955 (Box 15)
  - 1956-1970s, (3 folders) (Box 16)
  - People, Politics, Religion, 1975 and undated (2 folders and 1 volume)
  - undated, (3 folders) (Box 17)
- Genealogy Series
  - 1921-1974 (Box 17)
- Printed Material Series
  - 1912-1964, (3 folders) (Box 17)
  - 1965-1976, undated, (3 folders) (Box 18)
- Clippings Series
  - 1940-1968, (2 folders) (Box 18)
  - 1969-1975, undated (Box 19)
- Miscellaneous Series
  - Pictures, 1914?-1953, undated (Box 19)
  - 1936-1966, (4 folders)
  - 1967-1976, undated, (6 folders) (Box 20)
  - Photocopies, 1928-1968
- Oversize Material
  - Printed Material Series, 1948-1974 (Box 22)
  - Clippings Series--Scrapbooks, 1942-1948 (3) (Box 21)
  - Miscellaneous Series, 1936-1960s (Box 22)
  - Scrapbook, 1948 and undated (Box 22)